DAVID BERNARD

bernardd@uvic.ca · (250) 704 6482

SUMMARY

Highly professional *Marine Engineer* with over 12 years of hands on experience serving as a proven leader in the Royal Canadian Navy. Theoretical knowledge and practical experience in various engineering fields including machining, hydraulics, gas turbines, diesel engines, refrigeration, and reverse osmosis desalination. Strong computer skills include CAD, MS Office, and database design. History of positive evaluations describing excellent interpersonal skills as well as superior communication, leadership, and organizational abilities.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2002-Present Marine Engineer, ROYAL CANADIAN NAVY

Machine Shop Instructor/ Supervisor 2011-2013 · Canadian Forces Fleet School Esquimalt (CFFSE) Machine Shop Instructor/Supervisor

- Instructed up to 20 students in both a classroom and machine shop, with a high emphasis on safety.
- Managed machine shop operations, including tool crib staff, other instructors, and equipment.
- Developed and implemented lesson plans, including practical demonstrations and exams.
- · Designed projects and produced detailed CAD drawings.
- Developed MS Access database for automated marking of projects.
- Completed numerous shop improvements, including acquisition and implementation of automated tool crib accountability software.

2002-2011 · Various Other Positions, including:

Engineering Officer of the Watch Canadian Patrol Frigate Engineering Officer of the Watch

- Responsible for the safe and efficient operation of main machinery of a gas turbine/diesel propelled warship (CODOG) while in charge of the engineering watch.
- Responsible for supervision and safety of on watch personnel.
- Motivated, mentored, and trained junior personnel.
- Planned, coordinated, and conducted preventative and corrective maintenance.
- Diagnosed technical problems, then developed and implemented solutions to maintain/restore operability.

Maintenance Supervisor/ Planner Fleet Maintenance Facility Cape Breton Shop 182 Maintenance Supervisor/Planner

- Managed maintenance work groups, including planning, scheduling, and administration.
- Prioritized, managed, and supervised concurrent maintenance tasks, while ensuring a high standard of work.

EDUCATION

2013-2018 *(anticipated)*

University of Victoria

Bachelor of Engineering

GPA: 8.65 · Mechanical Engineering · Department of Mechanical Engineering Currently enrolled in 2nd year. Accomplishments include:

- 2014 · Engineering 120 (Robot Design): Finalist
- 2014 · Canadian Engineering Competition (Junior Design Team): Qualifier
- 2014 · Western Engineering Competition (Junior Design Team): 2nd Place
- 2013 · University of Victoria Engineering Competition (Junior Design Team): 1st Place
- 2013 · Engineering 110 (CRD Cycling Project): Winning Design

2012 ROYAL MILITARY COLLEGE OF CANADA

Royal Military College

Honours Standing · Officer Professional Military Education · Division of Continuing Studies Four courses (200-400 level) covering the following topics:

Leadership

Psychology

· Canadian politics

Ethics

· Canadian history

· Military history

2002-2004 Memorial University of Newfoundland

Technician Diploma

Marine Engineering · Fisheries and Marine Institute Two year college program. Topics included:

• Marine engineering knowledge

Hydraulics

· Workshop hand skills and machining

Thermodynamics

Electrotechnology

Mechanics

• Electronics, instrumentation, and controls

· Fluid mechanics

SKILLS & ABILITIES

Leadership

 Adept at employing a variety of leadership styles due to differing roles throughout military career.

Teamwork

• History of quickly and effectively integrating into diverse teams during short-term postings and maintaining team cohesion during demanding, long-term deployments.

Communication

- History of producing consistently high quality technical and administrative writing throughout academic and military careers.
- Instructional roles and oral exam board results show comfort with public speaking and ability to clearly convey complex technical concepts.

Dependable

- Entrusted with independent, high-responsibility roles such as Engineering Officer of the Watch.
- Performance during high-intensity engineering drills shows the ability to safely and effectively manage concurrent technical problems and emergencies while remaining calm.

Computer

CAD · SolidWorks, TurboCAD, AutoCAD, MS Visio

MS Office · Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Outlook, Access, Visio, Project

OTHER · LATEX, Microsoft Windows, C, Acrobat

CERTIFICATIONS & QUALIFICATIONS

Engineering

2011 · Engineering Officer of the Watch · Cert 3E Equivalent to Class 2 Power/Marine Engineer

Machining

2011 · Naval Machinist · Top Student Equivalent to Red Seal Machinist

Leadership

2009 · Primary Leadership Qualification Formal leadership course. Topics included:

· Leadership theory

• Conflict management

· Instructional techniques

Other Qualifications

- Standard First Aid
- LM2500 Gas Turbine Maintenance

• HRAI CFC/HCFC/HFC Control (Refrigeration and Air Conditioning)

OTHER

Decorations

South-West Asia Service Medal (SWASM) · Canadian Forces' Decoration (CD)

Activities

Kiteboarding · Camping · Cycling · Rock Climbing · Snowboarding / Skiing · Sailing

Intrests

Alternative Energy · Fabrication · Design · CAD